What is beauty?
We see it in people,
in landscapes, in experiences,
but what exactly is it?
In this series, we explore beauty.
Our instinct for beauty is older than we
are, it seems.
It existed tens of thousands of years
before we even had language.
We go back in time to discover the first
works of art ever created,
then trace [music] beauty's evolution
through to the present day.
We travel the length and breadth of the
world to discover different cultural
attitudes to beauty.
And we find out about the future, when
robots and artificial intelligence will
determine our aesthetic tastes.
We investigate [music] the value of
beauty,
the power of beauty,
and the other side of beauty.
How to make it and how to fake it. My
[music] name's Dominic Frisby and I'm a
writer from England.
And I've been asked to make a television
series in which we rediscover our sense
of beauty.
My journey begins here.
>> [music]
>> This is London. And I'm standing just
next to the Institute of Contemporary
Arts. Just over here, we have the
National Portrait Gallery. Beyond, the
British Museum. In this direction, the
Tate Gallery. Over here, the Victoria
and Albert Museum.
This is the art capital of the world.
But have you ever wondered, of all the
art that's bought and sold and on
display, not just here, but all over the
world, how much is genuine?
According to one study, as much as 50%
is forged.
You've heard about fake news. Today's
program is about fake beauty.
>> History is full of fraud and forgery.
And for some reason, human beings have
always delighted in tales of tricksters
and con men.
There's something about them that
captures the imagination.
We like it when somebody beats the
system and gets one over on the pompous
and powerful.
The more powerful and the more evil the
tricked, the more we like the trickster.
And so, we travel to
to tell the story of perhaps the
greatest trickster of the lot.
This is the municipal cemetery of
Deventer, a quiet Dutch town about an
hour's drive from Amsterdam.
And here, at this
almost anonymous-looking tombstone, lie
the ashes of perhaps the most notorious
forger who ever lived. This is the man
who duped the Nazis.
Han van Meegeren was born into a
middle-class family in 1889.
His love of art came at an early age,
but his father didn't approve, and so
van Meegeren took to painting on the
quiet.
When his father caught him, he would
make him repeat, "I know nothing. I am
nothing. I am capable of nothing."
His teacher at school imbued him with a
love of Dutch artist Vermeer.
His teacher loathed brash, contemporary
impressionist styles and taught van
Meegeren to paint in the style of the
Dutch Golden Age.
After school, his father insisted he
study architecture, which van Meegeren
did. But he also took art classes on the
side.
This boat house here in Delft, where he
studied, is one of the buildings [music]
he designed, and he used to love racing
boats here on the canals.
But, he never finished his course.
Instead, shortly after marrying his
first wife, who he met at this very boat
house, he went to art school full-time.
He left with all sorts of awards.
In 1917, he had his first public
showing, and by the 1920s, had become a
popular [music] and respected painter.
Then came the bad reviews.
Dutch art critics were more interested
in cubism, surrealism, and other
movements of the time. One critic said
Van Meegeren's talent was limited to
copying others. Another said he has
every virtue except originality.
Van Meegeren wrote a series of angry
articles in retaliation, and a kind of
rage grew inside of him at the failure
of the art world to recognize his
genius.
He set out to prove that he could not
only equal, but surpass the Dutch
masters. And with this in mind, in 1932,
now with his second wife, he moved to
the south of France.
>> Han van Meegeren is more or less the
prototype of a fortune.
He started out of revenge.
Um as a young guy, he he made great
portraits of of people, and people liked
his work. But, the critics said, "Well,
Mr. van Meegeren,
your work is good, but it's
it's not that good."
So, he thought, "So, I'm not that good.
I will show you that I'm better than you
think."
>> For 5 years, he studied the Dutch
greats. Not only their works, but their
techniques and their lives.
Vermeer, from here in Delft in Holland,
was the ideal candidate.
Not only was his work scarce and
valuable,
there was a period from his life from
which no work remained.
It was believed he was in Italy at the
time, so Van Meegeren set out to create
Vermeer's religious Italian period.
His first offering was the Supper at
Emmaus.
When Van Meegeren's Vermeer was first
displayed in Holland, it took the Dutch
art community by storm. Dr. Abraham
Bredius, perhaps the most pompous critic
of the day, a man for whom Van Meegeren
may have had considerable distaste,
gushed. He said, "It is a wonderful
moment in life to discover this hitherto
unknown painting." He declared it a
masterpiece. He said, "In no other
painting by the great master do we find
such sentiment."
A storm of excitement in this hitherto
undiscovered masterpiece followed. And
in 1937, Dirk Hannema, director of
Museum Boijmans, purchased the Supper at
Emmaus for the equivalent of about $5
million.
Van Meegeren used the money to buy a
lavish estate in Nice, where he painted
some of his greatest forgeries.
At the onset of war, he moved back to
Holland. And by the early 1940s, he was
worth a fortune. He used his money to
buy property after property by the
canals in some of the most exclusive
districts of Amsterdam.
But he was also drinking heavily. He'd
acquired a taste for sleeping pills.
And the quality of his work was
declining.
>> Van Meegeren forged Vermeer, and he did
so by finding a blind spot in a theory
by an art critic named Abraham Bredius,
who had for his entire life theorized
[music] that there had been a religious
period in Vermeer's work. And no work
had ever been found [music] that
substantiated this claim.
So, Van Meegeren
made work that fit [music] the theory
that Bredius had espoused. And Bredius
authenticated it because he was so
delighted to [music] find proof of what
he had always believed.
The work was abominable. Looked
absolutely nothing like anything you
would imagine a Vermeer to look like.
>> But despite its [music] dubious quality,
as it had been authenticated by a
so-called expert, The Supper at Emmaus
became an accepted part of the Vermeer
collection.
And thus was the door opened for further
forgeries from Vermeer's Italian
religious period.
One of these, Christ with the
adulteress, would enter the history
books.
>> Hermann Göring, notoriously ruthless,
after Hitler the most powerful man in
Nazi Germany. He was also a passionate
collector of art, and his collection,
most of it plundered, was enormous.
A German art dealer approached Göring
and said he had a contact in Holland who
might be able to get him a Vermeer. Not
only a Vermeer, one from his religious
Italian period. Göring jumped at the
idea, and eventually traded 137 of his
own works of art for this Vermeer, which
became his most prized possession. He
displayed it. He showcased it. He even
declared it the crown jewel in his
collection.
>> Eva.
>> Hello.
Arthur. Hello.
Tell me about the techniques that um Van
Meegeren used to to imitate Vermeer.
Tell me about the methods he used.
>> Well, he experimented for a long time.
He took months and months and he kept
experimenting with a mixture of
Bakelite, which was an early plastic, a
1920s plastic, and
and and oil paint,
pigments and oil. And he mixed this and
he tried again and again to see what
happened and it just would get
if you would bake it in an oven, he had
a special oven made and he would bake it
off and see what happened. And
in the end he got this result he wanted,
this old-looking painting and it was,
you know, he did it right.
>> So, would he paint it with this old
paint or would he paint it first and
then put it through this process to make
it to age it?
>> He painted it with this Bakelite mix
and then
you know, it was heated to, you know,
extensively and then
it it it it cracked in the way he wanted
it to crack.
And he rolled it up to get even more
cracks and then he rubbed in ink so it
would look like it was the dust of ages
and ages.
>> Okay.
>> And he used all these techniques to just
get it to look really old and people
believed him.
>> And he spent years practicing this
technique over and over again.
>> I thought it was
more like months and months, almost a
year. And he used the right colors. He
knew he had to use a type of yellow and
a type of blue that was very
convincing Vermeer color.
>> Okay.
>> After Göring was tried at Nuremberg, he
was sentenced to death.
An American soldier smuggled him some
cyanide with which he committed suicide
the day before he was supposed to be
executed.
On that same day, another soldier said
to him,
"By the way, your Vermeer,
it was fake."
At the end of the war, Göring's jewel
was discovered hidden behind some panels
in his home.
The painting [music] was traced back to
the German dealer who gave them Van
Meegeren's name.
Suddenly, Van Meegeren found himself on
trial for being a Nazi collaborator and
a plunderer of Dutch cultural property.
He was faced with the sentence of death.
"I painted the picture," he said. "It
isn't a Vermeer, it's a Van Meegeren."
Nobody believed him.
To prove his innocence, Van Meegeren
offered the court a proposition.
He would forge a Vermeer in front of a
panel of experts and witnesses.
The court agreed, and over the next 6
weeks, Van Meegeren painted his final
Vermeer, Jesus among the doctors.
And he did it while he was drunk and
high. "That was the only way he could
work," he said.
>> When you make a a forgery,
um you have to copy the lines of
of the the authentic masters. But, if
you copy it
line by line, people see it. It has to
be more fluent. And a lot of forgers
drink to make more fluent lines. So,
some of the forgers, when they start to
work, they first drink a few beers, take
a few pills, and then they um
go do what they want to do.
>> Experts [music] said it was of such a
high quality that Van Meegeren couldn't
possibly be lying, and the charge was
dropped.
He was sentenced to a year in prison.
"If I die in jail," he said, "they will
forget.
My paintings will become Vermeers once
more.
I didn't do it for the money. I did it
for the art.
But the day before his incarceration was
to begin, he died of a heart attack. He
was 58.
And here,
on his tombstone,
is written his name
and the years he lived. Nothing more.
Was he a hero?
Was he a villain?
Was he a victim?
It's left blank.
>> The forger adds real value into the
world by getting caught. Not because he
or she necessarily wants to, but when
that happens, does so very often in
terms of calling into question all of
the mechanisms of authority that tend to
be taken for granted.
The forger is in a sense a great artist
by virtue of the act of forgery, but
only when the forger gets caught. Only
when the forger ultimately fails to do
what he or she set out to do, does the
forger ascend to a higher plane.
>> During the course of his trial, Van
Meegeren said something rather profound.
"Yesterday, this painting was worth
millions of guilders, and experts and
art lovers would come from all over the
world and pay money to see it.
Today, it is worth nothing, and nobody
would cross the street to see it for
free.
Yet, the picture hasn't changed. What
has?"
>> After the war, Van Meegeren became quite
famous. He died, but Van Meegeren before
becoming a forger had made his own
style, his own work. So, some people
wanted to collect
the original Van Meegerens.
But,
the only one who could authenticate
these pieces was the son of Han van
Meegeren. And he thought, "When I'm the
only one who can authenticate pieces of
my dad, why don't I forge some of those
pieces?"
>> [laughter]
>> So, Van Meegeren was forced by his own
son.
>> Like father, like son.
The greatest forgers are almost always
skilled artists who feel somehow
rejected by the art world. Perhaps
they're masters of a style that isn't in
fashion, but for whatever reason, their
work goes unnoticed, unappreciated. A
critic deems it inconsequential.
They don't get the recognition they feel
they deserve, and they have a point to
prove. Excluded by the very world they
want to be a part of, they're going to
get their own back.
>> When an artist gets caught having made a
forgery, very often the excuse is that
the art world has been [music] too harsh
and somehow has not allowed that artist
to do what he or she believes is great
work.
And that may be true.
Though, if you look in many cases at the
sheer amount of work that these artists
make under other names, and the sheer
amount of money that they make at it,
you have to question whether that is the
case. So, art forgery, like any sort of
crime or in fact like any sort of
activity,
inherently has many different
motivations that vary from person to
person and even within an individual.
>> Art crime is almost as old as art
itself.
Before the the paint was dry on within
the the pyramids in Egypt, um
looters already were entering to steal
and forgery we know that for example in
200 BC when the Romans started to
collect Greek art like faces and um
statues,
the mark was flooded with fakes.
And at the time people had no not much
knowledge or technical um skills to to
distinguish fakes and authentic pieces.
But they didn't care that much at the
time. We know from Cicero that he was
more interested in how these [music]
pieces looked in his house than whether
they were fake or real.
So, it started
forgery started around 200, 300 BC. So,
that's quite a long time ago.
>> The motivation is almost always
financial.
In ancient Rome, ancient Greek statues
became extremely popular and to satisfy
demand some Romans took to forging them.
>> In ancient Rome you find many copies of
ancient Greek statuary, and our instinct
today is to look at the Roman copies as
being lesser, as somehow [music] being
as if they were forgeries. But, that to
me doesn't seem right because the Romans
were not looking at the Greek [music]
originals as being original in some sort
of a privileged sense. What really
mattered was the design. And therefore,
the Roman copy was for the Romans often
superior because it could take the Greek
design and could perfect it for the
Roman environment, [music] for whatever
garden
statuary would be placed in. And
moreover, could make it more perfect. Uh
it could improve upon the condition of
the original. And so, when we look at a
Roman copy, it really is important, I
think, that we not look at it
entirely from our own context of seeing
these works as somehow being copies,
fakes, or forgeries, but rather that we
appreciate that the design is what
mattered, and therefore that we try to
appreciate the design as instantiated in
these copies.
>> In the Dark Ages and medieval times,
there was an extremely brisk trade in
religious relics, many of which were of
dubious provenance.
>> During the Dark Ages, the Middle Ages,
there was not much interest for art.
People had other things on their minds.
The plague, wars. There was not much
money around. So,
um art collecting was not a real issue
at the time. But, people [music]
collected relics, like bones from
saints.
And
um
some saints, there were so many bones
attached to some of these [music] saints
that these people must have had two or
three bodies during their lifetime. So,
there were a lot of fakes around, of
course.
>> During the Renaissance, many painters
took on apprentices and actually taught
them to paint in their own style. The
master would then sell these works as
payment for his teaching.
This was considered tribute and not
forgery. And indeed, the distinction
between what is tribute, what is homage,
what is pastiche, and what is outright
forgery is often rather blurred.
>> Traditionally, we tend to think [music]
of a forgery as a form of fraud.
That is to say that it is distinct from
homage, where an homage is, generally
speaking,
done in public, where it is explicitly a
copy or a version of an original.
Therefore, a forgery always has a
subversive quality to it. It has a
quality of questioning the original,
which runs much more
deep, I believe, than an homage can do.
Because an homage simply can bring out
qualities in the original and
relationships between the original and
the copyist or the artist who has
undertaken the homage. The forgery can
bring out all sorts of latent qualities
that have to do with how we received the
original and how we relate to it today.
>> In Italy, the Renaissance had created a
new prosperous middle class, and they
wanted art. Ancient Roman statues became
extremely popular, but there were only
so many genuine ancient Roman statues
that could be unearthed. Supply had to
meet demand by alternative means.
>> We go to the Renaissance.
And that's a very special period. First
of all,
art collecting became a real business.
Popes, kings, merchants started to
collect art. There was money.
There was great art.
So, there was money and what was more
important some
artists for the first time in history
became famous.
Before the Renaissance, it was not about
the artist. It was about the piece of
art. Most of those art was religious
>> [music]
>> and
those pieces were inspired by gods and
dedicated to God. So, it was not about
the artist. They didn't even [music]
sign those works of art. But, in the
Renaissance, we see that some of these
artists become
pop stars. Michelangelo and other
people, they start to become famous.
People wanted their work.
So, this mix of a lot of money around
and artists who become
famous people, that's the perfect mix
for forgeries.
>> However, it seems that even some of the
Renaissance rock stars themselves might
have started out as forgers.
Once upon a time, right behind me here
in the heart of London, stood the
largest palace in the whole of Europe,
the Palace of Whitehall.
But, unfortunately, in 1698, it burned
down and among the many items destroyed
in the fire was a little-known statue by
a young Michelangelo called The Sleeping
Cupid.
When Michelangelo was just 21, his
patron, Lorenzo de Medici, died. His
hometown of Florence was in political
turmoil and the young struggling artist
found himself strapped for cash.
And at the time, ancient Roman statues
were selling rather well. So, the young
Michelangelo thought he would sculpt one
in the ancient style.
And when he came to sell it, he was
told, "Bury it in the ground, treat it
so it looks old, send it to Rome, there
they'll think it's an antique, and
you'll get more money for it." So,
that's just what Michelangelo did.
>> One of the most interesting stories
about forgers during the Renaissance is
Michelangelo.
The greatest of all.
Um we know that in the time of of um
Michelangelo, people wanted
authentic Roman statues. They didn't
like his work that much of Michelangelo.
[music] So, they they they said, "We
want authentic Roman pieces." So, what
did Michelangelo do?
He forged Roman statues. He made them,
he put them while in acidic grounds to
give them appearance of great age.
And then he sold them as authentic Roman
statues. So, can you imagine that
somebody somewhere in the world
is looking at a Roman statue of what he
thinks is a Roman statue worth 10,000
euros, which in reality is a
Michelangelo. [music]
Being worth tens of millions. So,
sometimes a forgery can be worth more
than an authentic piece.
>> Michelangelo had a kind of agent in Rome
called Baldassare del Milanese. And del
Milanese found a buyer for the
sculpture, a cardinal no less, one
Cardinal Riario, who paid the princely
sum of 200 ducats. But Michelangelo
didn't know any of that. He just took
his cut and forgot about it.
Two years later, Michelangelo went to
Rome looking for a patron.
He'd been recommended to visit Cardinal
Riario, and he took with him his letter
of recommendation.
The cardinal showed Michelangelo his
collection rather proudly, and there,
right in the middle of it, was the
Sleeping Cupid. "I sculpted that," said
Michelangelo, and the scam was rumbled.
That's when it was discovered that
Michelangelo had only been paid 30
ducats. The dealer had pocketed the
other 170.
The cardinal demanded his money back,
but not from Michelangelo.
The fact that Michelangelo had been able
to mimic so brilliantly the ancients had
impressed the cardinal, and he would
become Michelangelo's patron.
Skill was considered more important than
originality in those days, when ideas
were just part of the collective.
And Michelangelo's career took off.
First, he sculpted Bacchus, then Pietà.
Within 3 years, David was commissioned,
and within 10, he was standing on a
scaffolding, brush in hand, with his arm
outstretched towards the ceiling of the
Sistine Chapel, where he painted his
iconic work.
Del Milanese, meanwhile, had to give the
cardinal a refund. But when
Michelangelo's career took off, he sold
the sculpture for even more money as a
genuine Michelangelo.
How many more Michelangelos are there
out there masquerading as ancient Roman
statues?
Quite a few, I suspect.
>> Michelangelo was an art forger.
When people would loan him works by
[music] past masters, he often liked the
drawings so much that he would not only
copy them for his own education, but he
would keep them for himself. And he
would give back the copies that he had
made, passing them off as if they were
the originals.
And so today, we don't know which of
these works
are his as opposed to the masters who he
claimed they had been made by.
And as a result,
anything that we look at
from that period
could be, in fact, Michelangelo.
And therefore, we need to look at all
work from that period a little bit more
closely, thinking not only about our
appreciation for who made it based on
what name is on it, but also what hand
was responsible for it.
And that makes us, I think, more
attentive to all artwork.
>> Most forgers fall into their habit. They
don't set out to be forgers, it just
happens. By some accident of fortune,
often the need to earn a living, perhaps
they find themselves painting
reproductions, imitating, copying, and
they discover they're rather good at it.
When the money starts coming in, it's
very hard to turn down. That money's
nice.
And that's when they're trapped.
>> I believe that fakes are the great art
of our age, that forgeries are [music]
the masterpieces of our time. Not
because of their inherent qualities in
terms of the paintings or the sculptures
in their [music] own right, but because
of the act of forgery and the effect
that it has when a forger is exposed
on how we look at that work [music] and
how we look at ourselves.
To me, art is ultimately most
interesting [music] in our time where it
provokes anxiety about ourselves, about
our society, [music]
makes us look at our world and
scrutinize ourselves a little bit more
closely.
And when [music] a forgery is exposed,
that's exactly what happens. While
artwork [music] in a museum, say an
expressionist masterpiece or say a work
of pop art, may in some way suggest
various ways in which our society is
unsettled or unsettling, may illustrate
that fact. The forgery actually is
working
with
the unsettling qualities as the very
material of the fakery. That is to say
that the forger is using us
as the real material of the masterpiece
and is using us also as [music] the
audience of it. So that when we
see that we've been bamboozled,
what we find are all the ways in which
by way of our deception, we were not
attentive enough.
We were not paying attention
to phenomena or to attributes of our
society that we should have been.
And these attributes may range from
the degree to which we tend to invest
too much uh
of a sense of value in authority to the
degree to which [music] we may think of
authenticity as being a very simple sort
of operation.
All of this is up for re-examination
when the forger is at work. And that to
me is why forgers
deserve our begrudging respect.
>> And so to Switzerland to meet one of the
foremost companies in art analysis and
verification [music]
to discuss art forgery today.
>> Art forgery is much more widespread than
uh most collectors would expect. Uh
since 2009, since I'm in this industry,
uh we've seen a massive international
forgery scandal every year.
Um and every time auction houses, the
big galleries, the art dealers would
tell you, "That's the last time. That
was a one-off. That's bad luck. It won't
happen again." But in fact, every year
you have a new forgery scandal. So,
I think it's
pretty widespread.
>> SGS is in the business of inspection and
verification.
It acts as a kind of quality control for
traded goods, anything from chemicals to
agricultural produce, making sure they
meet certain standards. [music]
More recently, it has got into the
business of art. And that's because
[music] there is more fake art trading
hands than perhaps ever before.
>> There are three main reasons why uh we
find so many forgeries on the market
today. The first reason is the value of
art.
If an artwork is worth tens or hundreds
of million of dollars, of course for the
forger, it's very tempting
>> [music]
>> because by working just a few days or a
few weeks, you can make a a big sum of
money, a very good salary uh as a as a
painter by doing fakes. The second
reason is that many people buy art
nowadays as a form of investment. And
these people
probably don't have the same level of
knowledge and education
than collectors had in the past. And
these people are probably much easier to
cheat on than
a very well-educated collector. The
third reason is that modern contemporary
art forms like abstract art uh
may be perceived as easier to forge or
to copy. When you compare an abstract
composition
uh to a complicated old master painting
by Guardi or Canaletto or Tiepolo,
uh of course
it's more tempting for a forger to copy
an abstract composition because it's
simpler. It looks simpler.
>> SGS analyzes up to 400 artworks every
year and as many as 80% of them turn out
to be fakes, forgeries, or
misattributions.
This female nude, signed by French
painter of the [music] early 20th
century Fauvist movement Albert Marquet,
was sold with a certificate dating
[music] the painting to 1912.
When the owner wanted [music] to renew
the certificate, the Albert Marquet
authentication committee refused.
SGS [music] began their examination
using techniques which included
spectroscopy, infrared reflectography,
x-ray radiography, and pigment analysis.
>> Another composition was found underneath
[music]
upside down.
A tractor with farmers during the
harvest season.
Attractive enough, but notice the tires
on the tractor.
Tires such as these weren't used until
the 1930s or 1940s.
Thus, the terminus post quem, the
earliest possible date for the canvas is
then
there is no way the marquise on top
could have been painted in 1912.
>> Thanks to infrared reflectography and
X-radiography, we found out an
underneath composition
under this this painting
representing a totally different
subject, representing a tractor.
A tractor with a
harvest scene
and Um, the details that we can see in
the infrared reflectography
allow us to demonstrate
that the characteristic of this
structure are not compatible with a
model from 1912.
>> This painting of a doge was believed to
be of the 16th century Venetian school.
But was it a genuine 16th century work
or a later copy?
The painting had [music] been heavily
restored and ultraviolet light was used
to determine which parts were original
and which parts restored.
Once this was established, the original
parts were examined and pigments were
discovered which weren't used until the
19th century, making that the terminus
post quem. This was no 16th century
work.
>> One of the most interesting in recent
cases we have had here at SGS Art
Services was brought to us by Madame
Manuela de Kierkegaard.
She bought a painting made by her
grandfather, René Guiette.
And
it has a paysage and it's dated from
1953.
When the painting arrived,
very evidently we could see paint losses
that revealed very bright colors
that were contrasting with the current
composition that we see in paysage. The
analysis that we performed on paysage
were able to uncover underlying
composition.
>> When I received the x-ray from SGS,
I discovered a cubist
landscape with two figures.
And
it was a surprise. And suddenly studying
more
this x-ray, [music]
I suddenly remember that there was
somewhere into my archives a pictures of
René [music] Guiette who was painting a
cubist painting.
>> It was possible to compare with
photographs from the archive
and have an exact match of the painting
that was underneath.
It was also authored by René Guiette
from his cubist period that he then
later reused this canvas
in the '50s to make the composition that
we see today.
>> There is no technology presently
available that would enable us to
separate these two paintings. However,
it's unlikely Juliet would have wanted
that to happen.
>> He probably
painted over many Cubist paintings.
Why the Cubist paintings? There are also
many, many
possibilities.
Because of the flat surface or because
he was not liking his Cubist period
anymore.
>> For whatever reason, Juliet chose to
paint over [music] his previous efforts.
Perhaps we should respect that decision
and leave these paintings covered.
How many more covered works are there?
The answer to that, we will likely never
know.
Nor will we ever know just how big the
fake art market is.
Not all forgeries get detected despite
best efforts to safeguard against
misattribution and scams.
The spate of scandals which have rocked
the art world in recent years with
prized paintings being declared near
worthless fakes means there is
insecurity, fear, and paranoia amongst
museums, collectors, and auction houses
alike.
Fake works masquerading as originals
continue to litter the market. We will
never know just how many are fake.
Forgery is deceit and the aim of a
forger is not to be found out.
>> The value of fake art on the market is
probably impossible to
determine exactly.
What I can say is that
in
the massive forgery scandals [music]
we've seen, the international forgery
scandal we've seen in the last years,
they have caused millions of dollars of
damage to collectors, auction houses,
art dealers.
>> The estimates of forgeries on the market
range between 20% and 30%.
So, that means that almost all
museum collections or private
collections are full of fakes.
>> Just as methods of detection improve and
evolve, so do the forgers themselves.
They'll always be one step ahead. And
the higher valuations in the art market
go, the greater the lengths to which
forgers and their agents will go to get
a piece of this extraordinarily
lucrative action.
Particularly if the aspiring artist that
is the forger considers himself
overlooked and wants to get his own
back.
There will be forgery for as long as
there is a market for art.
Perhaps in the future, attitudes towards
originality will change and ideas will
once again be considered part of the
collective, just as they were before the
Renaissance. And the skills of
craftsmanship will be ascribed greater
value.
Art itself is a reproduction of life.
Perhaps art, by its very nature, is
therefore
false.
>> Some years ago I decided that I wanted
to be immortal
>> [music]
>> as so many artists want to be, but
I've never really been any [music] good
at painting or drawing, so I couldn't
take the usual means. So instead what I
did was I applied for a copyright on my
mind with the idea that I could continue
to think
after my own death
by licensing my mind to an artificial
intelligence. And I don't know right now
what to think of that because I'm still
alive, but maybe after I'm dead and I am
able to think about it, I'll have a
better idea of what it means to be alive
and what it means in terms of the degree
to which we are what we think
as opposed to the embodied selves that
we think of ourselves as being when we
think of ourselves as being alive.